美  丽  心  灵
普    林    斯    顿    大    学
1  9  4  7  年   9  月
是数学家赢得了世界大战
Mathematicians won the war.
是数学家破解了日本密码
Mathematicians broke the Japanese codes...
发明了原子弹
...and built the A-bomb.
同你们一样的数学家
Mathematicians... like you.
苏联的终极目标是赤化全世界
The stated goal of the Soviets is global communism.
在医学、经济
In medicine or economics,
科技、太空领域
in technology or space,
战线已经建立
battle lines are being drawn.
为了争取胜利，我们需要结果
To triumph, we need results.
可以发表和应用的结果
Publishable, applicable results.
那么你们当中谁将是下一个摩尔斯?
Now who among you will be the next Morse?
下一个爱因斯坦?
The next Einstein?
你们当中谁将是
Who among you will be the vanguard
民主、自由和探索的先锋?
of democracy, freedom, and discovery?
今天，我们将美国的未来
Today, we bequeath America's future
交到你们的手中
into your able hands.
欢迎加入普林斯顿，先生们
Welcome to Princeton, gentlemen.
汉森拿到卡内基奖学金居然还不满足
It's not enough Hansen won the Carnegie Scholarship.
他想要自己独享
No, he has to have it all for himself.
这是第一次由两人共享
It's the first time the Carnegie prize...
卡耐基奖学金，汉森都要气死了
...has been split. Hansen's all bent.
听说他一心想进入惠勒研究室
Rumor is he's got his sights set on Wheeler Lab,
就是麻省理工学院的新军事智囊团
the new military think tank at M.I.T.
今年他们只收一个人
They're only taking one this year.
而汉森当第一人选当习惯了
Hansen's used to being picked first.
是啊，他搞数学真是屈才了
Oh, yeah, he's wasted on math.
他应该去选总统
He should be running for president.
你的领带这么烂
There could be a mathematical explanation
一定有数学上的合理解释
for how bad your tie is.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我是尼尔森，专攻符号密码学
Neilson, symbol cryptography.
他破解过日本密码
Neils here broke a Jap code.
帮助了世界摆脱法西斯主义
Helped rid the world of fascism.
起码他对女生都是这么说的，是吧?
At least that's what he tells the girls, Neils?
我叫本德尔，专攻原子物理学
The name's Bender. Atomic physics.
-你是哪位?  -我迟到了吗?
-And you are?  -Am I late?
-是啊  -是啊，苏先生
-Yes.  -Yes, Mr. Sol.
噢，好吧，你好
Oh, good. Hi.
我是理查德・苏
Sol. Richard Sol.
这就是天才的负担
The burden of genius.
-他来了  -应酬这么多，时间却这么少
-There he is.  -So many supplicants, and so little time.
-苏先生  -你好啊，伙计
-Mr. Sol.  -How are you, sir?
-本德尔  -很高兴见到你
-Bender.  -Nice to see you.
恭喜你，汉森先生
Congratulations, Mr. Hansen.
谢谢
Thank you.
再给我一杯
I'll take another.
什么?
Excuse me?
万分抱歉，我以为你是服务生
A thousand pardons. I simply assumed you were the waiter.
给他留点面子，汉森
Play nice, Hansen.
给人留面子可不是汉森的派头
Nice is not Hansen's strong suit.
真是无心之过
Honest mistake.
唔，马丁・汉森
Well, Martin Hansen.
是马丁，没错吧?
It is Martin, isn't it?
没错，约翰，我就是
Why, yes, John, it is.
我猜你对误估已习以为常了吧
I imagine you're getting quite used to miscalculation.
我读过你的初稿
I've read your pre-prints.
两份都读过
Both of them.
有关纳粹密码文件的那份
The one on Nazi ciphers,
和有关非线性方程式的另外那份
and the other one on non-linear equations,
而我无比确信...
and I am supremely confident...
不管是哪一份都不具备...
that there is not a single seminal...
任何有价值或者新颖的观点
...or innovative idea in either one of them.
好好享受你的水果酒
Enjoy your punch.
各位，来会会约翰・纳什
Gentlemen, meet John Nash,
神秘的西弗吉尼亚州天才
the mysterious West Virginia genius.
著名的卡内基奖学金的另外那位得主
The other winner of the distinguished Carnegie Scholarship.
当然了
Of course.
真要命
Oh, Christ.
浪子室友到了
The prodigal roommate arrives.
室友?
Roommate?
天啊，饶了我吧
Oh, God, no.
你知道所谓的宿醉...
Did you know that having a hangover is...
就是体内没有足够的水份
...is not having enough water in your body
去执行克雷布斯循环吗?
to run your Krebs cycles?
这和你渴死时的发生的状况
Which is exactly what happens to you
是完全一样的
when you're dying of thirst.
所以说，渴死的感觉...
So, dying of thirst...
可能就像是宿醉...
would probably feel pretty much like the hangover...
最后特么醉死了一样
that finally bloody kills you.
约翰・纳什?
John Nash?
你好
Hello.
我叫查尔斯・赫曼
Charles Herman.
很高兴认识你
Pleased to meet you.
唔，正式宣布
Well, it's official.
我几乎又是个人了
I'm almost human again.
警官，我看到撞我的司机了
Officer, I saw the driver who hit me.
他的名字是"约翰尼沃克"（著名威士忌品牌）
His name was Johnny Walker.
呃，昨天晚上我...
Well, I got in last night
准时赶上了...
in time for...
英文系办的鸡尾酒会
English department cocktails.
鸡是我的
Cock was mine,
尾是那个特别年轻可人的小玩意儿
the tail belonged to a particularly lovely young thing
她还崇拜...
with a passion for...
D.H.劳伦斯（著名的情欲作家） 你不怎么容易被打扰，是吧?
D.H. Lawrence. You're not easily distracted, are you?
我是来工作的
I'm here to work.
唔，是吗? 那当然
Hmmm, are you? Right.
我明白了，哇哦!
I see. Crikey!
我的室友是个傻逼吗?
Is my roommate a dick?
我说，既然我们之间的冰山打不破
Listen. If we can't break the ice...
把它给淹了怎么样?
How about we drown it?
那么你有什么故事?
So what's your story?
一个从没出过家门的穷小孩?
You the poor kid that never got to go to Exeter or Andover?
虽然从小接受高等教育
Despite my privileged upbringing,
不过我也算是平衡发展
I'm actually quite well-balanced.
我和别人互相嫌弃的程度都差不多
I have a chip on both shoulders.
你大概就是比较擅长
Maybe you're just better
应付数字而不是人
with the old integers than you are with people.
我的小学老师，她跟我说
My first grade teacher, she told me
我有两个大脑
that I was born with two helpings of brain,
却只有半颗心
but only half a helping of heart.
-真的?  -嗯
-Really?  -Yeah.
哇! 她听上去很可爱!
Wow! She sounds lovely!
其实我...
The truth is that I...
我不喜欢人们
I don't like people much.
他们也不喜欢我
And they don't much like me.
怎么可能?
But why,
你这么聪慧又迷人
with all your obvious wit and charm?
说真的，约翰
Seriously, John.
数学...
Mathematics...
数学永远不能将你引向更高的真理
Mathematics is never going to lead you to a higher truth.
知道为什么吗?
And you know why?
因为它太无聊了，真的无聊
Because it's boring. It's really boring.
你知道半数以上的学生已经发论文了么?
You know half these schoolboys are already published?
我不能再在这些课上...
I cannot waste time with these classes...
和书上浪费时间了
and these books.
去记那些毫无说服力的假设!
Memorizing the weaker assumptions of lesser mortals!
我必须直接开始着手...
I need to look through...
研究管理动态学
to the governing dynamics.
找出它的原初理论
Find a truly original idea.
那是唯一的办法，能让我出人头地
That's the only way I'll ever distinguish myself.
能让我变得...
It's the only way that I'll ever...
举足轻重
Matter.
是的
Yes.
好吧，下一个是谁?
All right, who's next?
不玩了，我今天下够了，谢谢
No, I've played enough go for one day, thank you.
-来嘛  -我...我讨厌围棋
-Come on.  -I... I hate this game.
胆小鬼，统统都是!
Cowards, all of you!
没人站出来挑战我吗?
None of you rise to meet my challenge?
别啊，本德尔
Come on, Bender.
不管谁赢了，阿苏替他洗一学期的衣服
Whoever wins, Sol does his laundry all semester.
你们不觉得这很不公平吗?
Does that seem unfair to anyone else?
不觉得
Not at all.
-你们看他  -纳什!
-Look at him.  -Nash!
在倒着散步吗?
Taking a reverse constitutional?
我想推导出一个演算法
I'm hoping to extract an algorithm
来解释它们的移动
to define their movement.
神经病
Psycho.
喂，纳什，我还以为你退学了
Hey, Nash, I thought you dropped out.
话说你去上过课啥的吗?
You ever going to go to class or...?
上课会让你的脑筋迟钝
Classes will dull your mind.
破坏真正的创造力
Destroy the potential for authentic creativity.
哇，哇，这我倒不知道
Oh, oh, I didn't know that.
纳什会用他的才华会惊倒我们所有人的
Nash is going to stun us all with his genius.
不过换而言之也可能是
Which is another way of saying
他没胆子来跟我比试比试
he doesn't have the nerve to compete.
怕了吗?
You scared?
吓呆了
Terrified.
惊呆了，窘呆了
Mortified. Petrified.
蠢呆了...被你
Stupefied... by you.
替我洗衣服的时候别上浆，直接熨完折好就行
No starch. Pressed and folded.
我想问你件事，约翰
Let me ask you something, John.
尽管问，马丁
Be my guest, Martin.
本德尔和阿苏已经准确无误地完成了
Bender and Sol here correctly completed
柏瑞特推论的艾伦证明法
Allen's proof of Peyrot's Conjecture.
尚差强人意啦...
Adequate work...
没有创新
without innovation.
噢，受宠若惊! 你受宠若惊了没?
Oh. I'm flattered! You flattered?
受宠若惊
Flattered.
而我有两样武器纲要
And I've got two weapons briefs
正由国防部审查中
under security review by the D.O.D.
拾人牙慧
Derivative drivel.
而纳什的成就是：零
But Nash achievements: zero.
我是个耐心的人，马丁
I'm a patient man, Martin.
你到底想问什么?
Is there an actual question coming?
要是你永远找不出原创理论呢?
What if you never come up with your original idea?
最后惠勒研究室选择我，而不是你的时候...
How will it feel when I'm chosen for Wheeler...
你会是什么感觉?
...and you're not?
要是你输了呢?
What if you lose?
你不该赢的
You should not have won.
是我先走的，每一步都很完美
I had the first move, my play was perfect.
骄兵必败
The hubris of the defeated.
这个游戏有缺陷
The game is flawed.
先生们，这就是伟大的约翰・纳什
Gentlemen, the great John Nash.
你闷在这儿已经两天了
You've been in here for two days.
你知道汉森又发表了一篇报告吗?
You know Hansen's just published another paper?
可我连博士论文的主题都没有
I can't even find a topic for my doctorate.
唔，往好了看，你发明了橱窗艺术
Well, on the bright side, you've invented window art.
这是一场美式橄榄球队的比赛
This is a group playing touch football.
这是一群鸽子在争夺面包屑
This is a cluster of pigeons fighting over bread crumbs.
而这是一个女人
And this here is a woman
在追偷她钱包的男人
who is chasing a man who stole her purse.
约翰，你居然冷眼旁观一桩抢夺案
John, you watched a mugging.
真不可思议
That's weird.
在竞争的状态下总有人会输
In competitive behavior someone always loses.
这点连我的小侄女都懂，约翰
Well, my niece knows that, John,
而她大概这么高
and she's about this high.
你看，如果我能推导出一种均衡
See, if I could derive an equilibrium
在这种情境中优势可逆
where prevalence is a non-singular event,
没有人会输
where nobody loses,
你能想象这会带来多大的影响吗
can you imagine the effect that would have
在冲突情境下，还有武装谈判...
on conflict scenarios, and arms negotiations...
你上次吃东西是什么时候?
When did you last eat?
和货币交换中?
...currency exchange?
就是吃饭
You know, food.
你一点也不尊重幻想
You have no respect for cognitive reverie,
你知道吗?
you know that?
没错
Yes.
可披萨...
But pizza...
我对披萨可是充满了尊重
Now, pizza I have enormous respect for.
当然还有啤酒
And of course beer.
我尊重啤酒
I have respect for beer.
我尊重啤酒!
I have respect for beer!
-晚上好，尼尔森  -喂，纳什
-Good evening, Neils.  -Hey, Nash.
谁赢了? 这个你还是那个你?
Who's winning? You or you?
-晚上好，纳什  -你们好
-Evening, Nash.  -Hey, guys.
你好，纳什
Hey, Nash.
他在看你
He's looking at you.
你确定?
Are you sure?
你好，纳什
Hey, Nash.
尼尔森要你过去
Neils is trying to get your attention.
-你一定在开玩笑呢  -不是吧
-You're joking.  -Oh, no.
勇敢地去
Go with God.
一定要失身哟
Come back a man.
幸运与勇者同在
Fortune favors the brave.
炸他个屁滚尿流
Bombs away.
各位，需要我提醒你们我的胜算
Gentlemen, might I remind you that my odds of success
在每试一次之后都会急剧增加吗?
dramatically improve with each attempt?
保证绝对精彩
This is going to be classic.
你是不是想请我喝杯酒
Maybe you want to buy me a drink.
我不知道我应当说些什么
I don't exactly know what I'm required to say
来让你跟我发生性关系
in order for you to have intercourse with me,
不过咱们能不能就当我已经说过了?
but could we assume that I said all that?
我们基本上是要谈液体交流的事，对吧?
Essentially we're talking about fluid exchange, right?
所以，我们可以直接切入性的主题吗?
So, could we just go straight to the sex?
噢，真贴心
Oh, that was sweet.
晚上玩得开心，混蛋!
Have a nice night, asshole!
小姐们，等等!
Ladies, wait!
我最喜欢液体交流那一段
I... I especially liked the bit about fluid exchange.
真的很撩人
It was really charming.
陪我走走，约翰
Walk with me, John.
我一直想和你谈谈
I've been meaning to talk with you.
教授们已经完成了期中审核
The faculty is completing mid-year reviews.
我们正在决定如何分配学生
We're deciding which placement applications to support.
惠勒研究室，先生，那是我的第一选择
Wheeler, sir. That would be my first choice.
而且事实上，我没有第二选择，先生
And actually, I don't really have a second choice, sir.
约翰，其他的人都按时上课
John, your fellows have attended classes.
他们写了论文，他们发刊了
They've written papers. They've published.
我还在研究，先生，我的...
I'm still searching, sir, for my...
你的原创理论，我知道
Your original idea, I know.
管理动态学，先生
Governing dynamics, sir.
很有想法，约翰，可是恐怕
It's very clever, John, but I'm afraid
这还远远不够
it's just not nearly good enough.
-我帮您拿?  -谢谢
-May I?  -Thank you.
我一直在研究 "流形嵌入"
I've been working on manifold embedding.
我的 "议价策略" 理论已经初见成效
My bargaining stratagems are starting to show some promise.
如果您可以再安排一次
If you could just arrange another meeting,
我和爱因斯坦教授会面
if you'd be kind enough, with Professor Einstein...
-就是我再三请求过您的  -约翰，听我说
-I've repeatedly asked you for that.  -Now, John.
我会让他看看我修改过的...
I'd be able to show him my revisions on his...
约翰
John.
你看到他们在做什么了吗?
Do you see what they're doing in there?
-恭喜  -非常感谢
-Congratulations.  -Thank you so much.
恭喜，麦克斯教授
Congratulations, Professor Max.
那些笔
It's the pens.
是为一名院内成员所准备
Reserved for a member of the department
用以肯定其终生成就的
that makes the achievement of a lifetime.
现在你看到了什么，约翰?
Now what do you see, John?
赞许
Recognition.
做得好，教授，做得好
Well done, Professor, well done.
你看到圆满了吗?
Well, try seeing accomplishment.
有什么分别吗?
Is there a difference?
约翰
John,
你一直心不在焉
you haven't focused.
对不起，不过到目前为止
I'm sorry, but up to this point,
你的履历压根不足以保证你能得到任何职位
your record doesn't warrant any placement at all.
再见
Good day.
还有我的致意，先生
And my compliments to you, sir.
非常感谢
Thank you so much.
怎么就是看不出来呢
I can't see it.
天啊，约翰
Jesus Christ, John.
我不能失败
I can't fail.
这是我的全部呀
This is all I am.
来吧，咱们出去走走
Come on, let's go out.
我必须做些成绩出来
I got to get something done.
光盯着天空不是办法
I can't keep staring into space.
约翰，够了!
John, enough!
我得去面对墙壁，循规蹈矩...
Got to face the wall, follow their rules...
好，你想来点硬的? 好啊!
Fine, you want to do some damage? That's fine!
-别磨叽了  -看他们的书，上他们的课...
-But don't mess around.  -Read thier books, do their classes...
去啊! 去，把脑袋给撞破! 一头撞死自己!
Come on! Go on, bust your head! Kill yourself!
约翰，赶紧，别磨叽了
John, do it. Don't mess around.
一头撞死啊!
Bust your head!
去啊，把你那没用的脑袋给撞碎
Go on,bust that worthless head wide open.
该死的，查尔斯!
Goddamn it, Charles!
你到底有什么毛病?!
What the hell is your problem?!
我没毛病
It's not my problem.
你也没毛病
And it's not your problem.
是他们有毛病
It's their problem.
解决之道不是面对墙壁
Your answer isn't face the wall.
它在外头...在你工作的地方
It's out there... where you've been working.
它可真重
That was heavy.
看来牛顿这家伙说得没错
That Isaac Newton fellow was right.
-他可真厉害  -聪明的家伙
-He was onto something.  -Clever boy.
别担心，是我的东西
Don't worry, that's mine.
我等会儿就去收拾
I'll come and get it in a minute.
噢，天呐
Oh, God.
好戏来了，先生们
Incoming, gentlemen.
深呼吸
Deep breaths.
纳什，你最好从翻论文里
Nash, you might want to stop shuffling
先抽身几秒钟
your papers for five seconds.
我不请你们喝啤酒
I will not buy you gentlemen beer.
噢，我们不是来喝啤酒的，朋友
Oh, we're not here for beer, my friend.
你们是不是也觉得她最好以慢动作移动?
Does anyone else feel she should be moving in slow motion?
她会要求一个盛大的婚礼吗，你们觉得?
Will she want a large wedding, you think?
我们该用剑决斗吗? 还是黄昏时比枪法?
Shall we say swords, gentlemen? Pistols at dawn?
你们怎么都忘了?
Have you remembered nothing?
还记得现代经济学之父
Recall the lessons of Adam Smith,
亚当・史密斯教你们的吗
the father of modern economics.
"在竞争中...
"In competition...
个人的野心往往会促进公共福利"
individual ambition serves the common good."
-没错  -各凭本事，朋友们
-Exactly.  -Every man for himself, gentlemen.
出局的人负责去黏住她的朋友
And those who strike out are stuck with her friends.
我不会出局的
I'm not gonna strike out.
你可以把金发美女带到水边
You can lead a blonde to water,
但你不能逼她喝水
but you can't make her drink.
我觉得他可没说过这个...
I don't think he said that...
都别动...她在看这边了
Nobody move... She's looking over here.
她在看纳什
She's looking at Nash.
好吧，姑且算他现在占上风
Oh, God. He may have the upper hand now,
但等他一开口，啧啧
but wait until he opens his mouth.
还记得上次吗?
Remember the last time?
噢，对，那一次可真是载入史册
Oh, yes, that was one for the history books.
亚当・史密斯需要修订他的理论了
Adam Smith needs revision.
你在说什么?
What are you talking about?
如果我们都去追那个金发美女...
If we all go for the blonde...
一定会互相拆台
we block each other.
到时候谁都别想得到她
Not a single one of us is gonna get her.
然后我们去找她的朋友
So then we go for her friends,
她们肯定会泼我们冷水
but they will all give us the cold shoulder
因为没人愿意当二手选择
because nobody likes to be second choice.
要是没人去追那个金发美女呢?
Well, what if no one goes for the blonde?
那我们之间既互不侵犯
We don't get in each other's way,
也没有羞辱到其他女孩
and we don't insult the other girls.
这是咱们赢得芳心的唯一办法
That's the only way we win.
是咱们都能干一炮的唯一办法
That's the only way we all get laid.
亚当・史密斯曾说过
Adam Smith said
最好的结果来自于...
the best result comes...
团体里的所有人都去做
from everyone in the group doing
对他自身最有利的事，对吧?
what's best for himself, right?
他是这么说的，对不对?
That's what he said, right?
不完整，不完整，好吧?
Incomplete. Incomplete, okay?
因为最好的结果来自于...
Because the best result will come...
团体里的所有人
from everyone in the group
都去做对他自身和团体最有利的事
doing what's best for himself and the group.
纳什，你要是想拿这套歪理去独占那位金发美女
Nash, if this is some way for you to get the blonde on your own,
你就可以滚了
you can go to hell.
管理动态学，各位
Governing dynamics, gentlemen.
管理动态学，亚当・史密斯...
Governing dynamics. Adam Smith...
他错了
was wrong.
-又来啦  -小心点，小心点
-Oh, here we go.  -Careful, careful.
谢谢你
Thank you.
C(S)等于C(T)
"C" of "S" equals "C" of "T".
你知道这会推翻一百五十年来
You do realize this flies in the face
牢不可破的经济理论吧?
of a 150 years of economic theory?
是的，我知道，先生
Yes, I do, sir.
那可是相当地肆意妄为，你不觉得吗?
That's rather presumptuous, don't you think?
是，先生
It is, sir.
好吧，纳什先生
Well, Mr. Nash,
既然做出了这样一个量级的重大突破
with a breakthrough of this magnitude,
我相信你可以去任何你想去的地方
I'm confident you will get any placement you like.
惠勒研究室
Wheeler Labs,
会请你介绍两位组员
they'll ask you to recommend two team members.
太棒了!
Yes!
斯提尔斯和弗兰克应该很合适
Stills and Frank are excellent choices.
苏和本德尔，先生
Sol and Bender, sir.
苏和本德尔都是非常优秀的数学家
Sol and Bender are extraordinary mathematicians.
但纳什先生，你可曾想过，苏和本德尔
Has it occurred to you, Mr. Nash, that Sol and Bender
或许另有打算?
might have plans of their own?
乖乖! 惠勒研究室，我们成了!
Baby! Wheeler, we made it!
干杯  干
Cheers, cheers, cheers!
祝...
To...
好吧，尴尬时刻到了，先生们
Okay, awkward moment, gentlemen.
管理动态学
Governing dynamics.
-恭喜，约翰  -谢谢
-Congratulations, John.  -Thanks.
-干杯!  -敬惠勒研究室!
-Toast!  -To Wheeler Labs!
敬惠勒研究室!
To Wheeler!
五   角   大   楼   1 9 5 3 年
五   年   后
将军，惠勒研究室的分析专家到了
General, the analyst from Wheeler Lab is here.
纳什博士，您的外套?
Dr. Nash, your coat?
谢谢您
Thank you, sir.
博士
Doctor.
将军，这位是惠勒研究室的领导人约翰・纳什博士
General, this is Wheeler team leader Dr. John Nash.
很高兴你能来，博士
Glad you could come, Doctor.
您好
Hello.
这边走
Right this way.
我们截获由莫斯科发出的无线电报
We've been intercepting radio transmissions from Moscow.
电脑无法查出它的模式
The computer can't detect a pattern,
但我确信是密码
but I'm sure it's code.
何以见得，将军?
Why is that, General?
你有过那种 "就是知道" 的感觉吗，纳什博士?
Ever just know something, Dr. Nash?
经常会
Constantly.
我们研发了几个密码索引
We've developed several ciphers.
你可以看看我们的初步资料...
If you'd like to review our preliminary data...
博士?
Doctor?
6-7-3-7
0-3-6...
8-4-9-4
8-4-9-4.
9-1-4-0-3-4
9-1-4-0-3-4.
我要一份地图
I need a map.
40-6-13-0-8-67-46-9-0
40-6-13-0-8-67-46-9-0,
斯达基角，缅因州
Starkey Corners, Maine.
48-03-01
48-03-01,
91-26-35
91-26-35.
波吉特草原，明尼苏达州
Prairie Portage, Minnesota.
这些都是经度和纬度
These are latitudes and longitudes.
至少还有十个
There are a least 10 others.
这似乎是进入美国边境的路线顺序
They appear to be routing orders across the border into the U.S.
太惊人了
Extraordinary.
先生们
Gentlemen,
我们需要进一步研究
we need to move on this.
那位老大哥是谁?
Who's big brother?
你为国家贡献良多，年轻人
You've done your country a great service, son.
-上尉!  -是，长官
-Captain!  -Yes, sir.
替纳什博士带路
Accompany Dr. Nash.
将军，俄国人有什么动向?
What are the Russians moving, general?
罗杰上尉会送你
Captain Rogers will escort you
到不受限区，博士
to the unrestricted area, Doctor.
谢谢
Thank you.
纳什博士，请跟我来
Dr. Nash, follow me, please.
是纳什博士
It's Dr. Nash.
好的
All right.
惠    勒    国    防    研    究    室
麻 省 理 工 学 院
-谢谢你，先生  -在五角大楼打出全垒打了吗?
-Thank you, sir.  -Home run at the Pentagon?
他们是不是把 "机密 "两个字
Have they actually taken the word "classified"
从字典里给删掉了?
out of the dictionary?
嗨，冷气机又坏了
Oh, hi. The air conditioning broke again.
我在这儿都快融化了
How am I supposed to be in here saving the world
还怎么去拯救世界啊?
if I'm melting?
对你深表同情
Our hearts go out to you.
你们懂的，四年里去五角大楼转了两次
You know, two trips to the Pentagon in four years.
那你比我们多去了两次
That's two more than we've had.
好戏还在后面，约翰
It gets better, John.
我们刚接到最新的光荣任务
Just got our latest scintillating assignment.
你们知道的，俄国人已经搞出氢弹了
You know, the Russians have the H-bomb,
纳粹的魔爪正在伸向南美
the Nazis are repatriating South America,
中国有两百八十万的常备军
the Chinese have a standing army of 2.8 million,
而我却在做水坝的压力测试
and I am doing stress tests on a dam.
你可上了 "财富" 杂志的封面...第二回了
You made the cover of Fortune... again.
请注意用的词是 "你"，不是"我们"
Please note the use of the word "you", not "we".
应该只有我一个人才对
That was supposed to be just me.
所以说他们不但抢走了我的菲尔兹奖
So not only do they rob me of the Fields medal,
现在还把我和这些二流写手，这些三脚猫学者们
now they put me on the cover of Fortune magazine
一起放在 "财富" 的封面上
with these hacks, these scholars of trivia.
约翰，才华和才华横溢
John, exactly what's the difference
到底有什么差别?
between genius and most genius?
差别大了
Quite a lot.
一个是爹一个是儿子
He's your son.
总之，你只有十分钟了
Anyway, you've got 10 minutes.
我有一万个十分钟
I've always got 10 minutes.
在你去上新课之前?
Before your new class?
能不能请医生 (doctor) 开张病假单?
Can I not get a note from a doctor or something?
你就是博士 (doctor) ，约翰，不行
You are a doctor, John, and no.
拜托，你知道这里的规定
Now, come on, you know the drill,
我们从学校那儿拿到这些牛逼的设备
we get these beautiful facilities,
学校就要用这些当今美国最伟大的脑子
M.I.T. gets America's great minds of today
去教那些未来最伟大的脑子
teaching America's great minds of tomorrow.
可怜的傻逼们
Poor bastards.
好了，在学校过得愉快
Now, have a nice day at school.
上课铃要响了
The bell's ringing.
饥渴稚嫩的未来之星
The eager young minds of tomorrow.
可以留一个不要关吗，教授?
Can we leave one open, Professor?
实在太热了，先生
It's really hot, sir.
跟课堂安静相比
Your comfort comes second
你的舒适度只能往后排
to my ability to hear my own voice.
我个人认为
Personally,
这堂课会浪费
I think this class will be a waste...
你们的时间...
of your...
而更糟糕的是会浪费...
And what is infinitely worse...
我的时间
my time.
不过
However,
既然来了，那就说好
here we are. So...
你们来不来上课都行
you may attend or not.
至于完不完成作业你们乐意就成
You may complete your assignments at your whim.
咱们这就开始
We have begun.
小姐
Miss.
打扰一下!
Excuse me!
我们有点小小的问题
We have a little problem.
关上窗户这里会特别热
It's extremely hot in here with the windows closed
开着又会特别吵
and extremely noisy with them open.
所以，我想能不能请你们
So, I was wondering if there was any way you could,
先修别的地方，大概45分钟就好?
I don't know, maybe work someplace else for about 45 minutes?
-没问题  -谢谢你们!
-Not a problem.  -Thank you so much!
-休息一下!  -好嘞!
-At a break!  -Got it!
你们会发现在多变性的微积分中
As you will find in multivariable calculus,
往往会有...
there is often...
一题多解的情况
a number of solutions for any given problem.
如我所言，这道题
As I was saying, this problem here
有些人会解上好几个月
will take some of you many months to solve.
而其他人
For others among you,
则会花上一辈子的时间
it will take you the term of your natural lives.
纳什教授
Professor Nash.
我是威廉・帕彻
William Parcher.
老大哥
Big brother,
为您效劳
at your service.
我能为国防部做些什么?
What can I do for the Department of Defense?
你是来替我加薪的吗?
Are you going to to give me a raise?
咱们散散步
Let's take a walk.
-你在五角大楼的工作让人钦佩  -的确如此
-Impressive work at the Pentagon.  -Yes, it was.
奥本海默 (原子弹之父) 说过
Oppenheimer used to say,
"天才会先于问题而看见答案"
"Genius sees the answer before the question."
你认识奥本海默?
You knew Oppenheimer?
他的计划就是在我的监督之下进行的
His project was under my supervision.
哪个计划?
Which project?
那个计划
That project.
其实并没有那么简单，你明白吗?
It's not that simple, you know?
你们可结束了战争啊
Well, you ended the war.
我们烧死了十五万人
We incinerated 150,000 people in a heartbeat.
伟大的事迹都伴随着巨大的代价，帕彻先生
Great deeds come at great cost, Mr. Parcher.
评判是非功过的权力
Well, conviction, it turns out,
可是旁观者才拥有的奢侈品，纳什先生
is a luxury of those on the sidelines, Mr. Nash.
我会试着记住的
I'll try and keep that in mind.
那么约翰，你没家人
So John, no family,
也没有密友...
no close friends...
何以至此?
Why is that?
我喜欢归结于自己是个独狼的缘故
I like to think it's because I'm a lone wolf.
不过主要是因为人们不喜欢我
But mainly it's because people don't like me.
唔，在某些需要苦心孤诣的时候
Well, there are certain endeavors
缺乏人际交往
where your lack of personal connection
反倒会被视为一项优势
would be considered an advantage.
这里是管制区
This is a secure area.
他们认识我
They know me.
你来过这里吗?
Have you ever been here?
在刚来的时候他们介绍说
We were told during our initial briefing
这些仓库都被废弃了
that these warehouses were abandoned.
不完全正确
That's not precisely accurate.
等我告诉了你下面的内容
By telling you what I'm about to tell you,
就相当于把你的保密权限提升到了
I am increasing your security clearance
最高机密
to top secret.
泄露机密资料会招致牢狱之灾
Disclosure of secure information can result in imprisonment.
懂吗?
Get it?
什么行动?
What operation?
由战略行动办公室制作
这东西挺好用的
Those are a good idea.
这家工厂位于柏林
This factory is in Berlin.
我们在战争行将结束时占领了它
We seized it at the end of the war.
纳粹工程师正试图
Nazi engineers were attempting
造出轻型原子弹
to build a portable atomic bomb.
苏联在我们前面抵达了这个设施
The Soviets reached this facility before we did,
我们丢失了该死的资料
and we lost the damn thing.
五角大楼的路线顺序
The routing orders at the Pentagon,
它们跟这个有关，不是吗?
they were about this, weren't they?
苏联内部并没有人们所认为的那样统一
The Soviets aren't as unified as people believe.
一小股自称 "新自由" 的红军
A faction of the Red Army calling itself Novaya Svobga,
控制了原子弹
"the New Freedom" has control of the bomb
并且打算在美国本土引爆
and intends to detonate it on U.S. soil.
他们打算造成最大的平民伤亡
Their plan is to incur maximum civilian casualties.
人类是能做到可以想见的
Man is capable of as much atrocity
最极端的残忍的
as he has imagination.
新自由在美国有间谍
New Freedom has sleeper agents here in the U.S.
麦卡锡议员是个白痴
McCarthy is an idiot,
不幸的是这并不意味着他是错的
but unfortunately that doesn't make him wrong.
新自由是通过报纸和杂志上的密码
New Freedom communicates to its agents
同其间谍进行通讯的
through codes imbedded in newspapers and magazines,
这正是我们需要你的地方
and that's where you come in.
你瞧，约翰
You see, John,
你鹤立鸡群的地方
what distinguishes you
在于你是...
is that you are,
简单来说
quite simply,
一名我所见过最好的、天生的密码破译者
the best natural code-breaker I have ever seen.
你到底要我干什么?
What exactly is it that you would like me to do?
把这份期刊列表记下来
Commit this list of periodicals to memory.
仔细浏览每期新刊
Scan each new issue,
只要发现密码
find any hidden codes,
就破解掉它
decipher them.
把下巴放在下巴台上
Place your chin on the chin rest.
凝视灯光
Stare into the light.
脉搏88，正常
Pulse 88, regular.
这个会有点不舒服
Okay, this may be a little uncomfortable.
有点痛，对不对?
That's got a little zap to it, doesn't it?
他只是植入了一个镭二极管
He just implanted a radium diode.
别担心，很安全
Don't worry, it's safe.
它会周期性衰变
The isotope decays predictably.
使得这些数字定期更换
As a result, these numbers change over time.
那是你进入投信点的密码
They're the access codes to your drop spot.
那我现在成什么了，一个密探?
So what am I now, a spy?
进来
Come.
天呐，你一定很重要
Boy, you must be really important.
没事了，麦克
It's all right, Mike.
你在做什么?
What are you working on?
这是机密
Classified.
我们已经等了半个钟头
Everyone waited half an hour.
等什么?
For?
你的课呀
Class.
你今天没来上课
You missed class today.
噢，我估摸着...
Oh. I suspect that...
没人会想见我的
nobody missed me.
你写在黑板上的问题...
The problem that you left on the board...
我解出来了
I solved it.
不可能
Oh, no you didn't.
你连看都没看
You didn't even look.
我并没有说向量场是有理函数
I never said that the Vector Fields were rational functions.
你的解很优雅
Your solution is elegant.
但是在这种特殊情况下
Though on this particular occasion,
完全错误
ultimately incorrect.
你还在这儿
You're still here.
我还在这儿
I'm still here.
为什么?
Why?
我在想...
I'm wondering,
纳什教授
Professor Nash,
我能不能请你去吃晚餐
if I can ask you to dinner.
你总要吃饭吧?
You do eat, don't you?
哦，偶尔会去，嗯
Oh, on occasion, yeah.
都是一个人，像普罗米修斯被锁在巨石上
Table for one. Prometheus alone chained to the rock
只有鸟在他头上飞，你明白那是什么感觉
with the bird circling overhead, you know how it is.
不，我觉得你不会...
No, I expect that you wouldn't...
你不会明白
You wouldn't know.
如果你把地址留在我的办公室里
If you leave your address with my office,
我就在星期五晚上八点去接你
I'll pick you up Friday at 8:00
然后去吃饭
and we'll eat.
还有件事，你有名字吗?
One more thing. Do you have a name,
还是要我继续叫你 "小姐"?
or should I just keep calling you "miss"?
州长，这位是...
Governor, may I present...
艾丽西娅・劳德小姐
Miss Alicia Larde.
教授，请你和州长合照一张
Professor, please. You and the governor.
请等一下，抱歉
Wait, one second. I'm sorry.
多洗一张给我
I want a copy of this.
这是我们第一次约会
First big date and all, you know.
所以你们一定得看着养眼才行
So, you boys need to look good.
如果你说想要完全自然不加修饰
Which is not a state you find yourselves in
那可不成
altogether naturally.
行，好多了
There. Better.
我在让他对我刮目相看
I'm surprising him.
继续努力
You just keep on surprising him.
教授
Professor.
上帝一定是个画家
God must be a painter.
否则怎么会有这么多种颜色?
Why else would we have so many colors?
那么你是个画家?
So you're a painter?
我可不是这么说的
That's not actually what I said,
不过，没错...
but, yes...
我是
I am.
看这儿
Here.
看我，你约会的对象
Me. Your date?
我正在学习人类互动和社交礼仪
Practice human interaction and social comportment.
似乎还蛮有道理
That's a plan.
替我拿杯香槟会是个好主意
Champagne would be lovely.
我会在外面等你
I'll be outside.
我这就去拿
I will get the champagne.
谢谢你
Oh, thank you.
谢谢你的手帕
Thank you for that.
别，你留着
No, keep it.
我相信在做决定的时候它会带给你好运
I believe in deciding things will be good luck.
你信吗?
Do you?
我不相信运气
No. I don't believe in luck.
但我相信价值分配
But I do believe in assigning value to things.
我曾试着想数尽它们
I once tried to count them all.
甚至曾数到第4348颗
I actually made it to 4,348.
你真的很古怪
You are exceptionally odd.
我猜你一定很受女孩们欢迎
I bet you're very popular with the girls.
我们算是一对怪胎
A pair of odd ducks, then.
挑一个形状
Pick a shape.
什么?
What?
随便选个形状，像动物之类的
Pick a shape. An animal... anything.
好
Okay.
雨伞
An umbrella.
再来一次
Do it again.
-再来一次嘛  -好的
-Do it again.  -All right.
你想看什么?
What would you like?
章鱼
An octopus.
"人造生物，已存活三天"
"过期的传单在家里最安全"  "包豪斯建筑的领导者"
"如何能在退休15年后每月仍有三百美金的收入"
"新西门耐子地板对儿童很安全，因为它含有乙烯基!"
"人造生物"
"机密"
"信件"
你不太爱讲话，是吗?
You don't talk much, do you?
我不能和你谈公事，艾丽西娅
I can't talk to you about my work, Alicia.
我不是指公事
I don't mean work.
我发现通过改善互动方式
I find that polishing my interactions
去增加我的社交能力
in order to make them sociable
需要耗费巨大的努力
requires a tremendous effort.
我有一种倾向，就是喜欢以直接的方式
I have a tendency to expedite information flow...
去传递信息流
by being direct.
结果通常很不愉快
I often don't get a pleasant result.
试试我
Try me.
好
All right.
我很喜欢你
I find you attractive.
而你对我这么主动
Your aggressive moves towards me
证明你也喜欢我
indicate that you feel the same way.
不过，照规矩
But still, ritual requires that
我们在做爱之前还要来上几段
we continue with a number of platonic activities
柏拉图式的爱情活动
before we have sex.
我正在进行那种活动
I am proceeding with those activities,
然而就事实而言
but in point of actual fact,
我真正想做的只是
all I really want to do
尽早和你发生性关系而已
is have intercourse with you as soon as possible.
你是不是该抽我了?
Are you gonna slap me now?
这个结果怎么样?
How was that result?
你在做什么?
What are you doing?
我想从期刊中识别出
I'm attempting to isolate patterned re-occurrences
那些不断重复的模式来
within periodicals over time...
你呢?
and you?
纳什先生，你讲话很奇怪
You talk funny, Mr. Nash.
我认识你吗?
Do I know you?
我叔叔说你很聪明但不太友善
My uncle says you're very smart but not very nice,
叫我不用太介意，如果你对我凶的话
so I shouldn't pay no mind if you're mean to me.
你的叔叔是谁?
And who might your uncle be?
浪子室友
The prodigal roommate...
回来了
returns.
-过来  -查尔斯
-Come here.  -Charles, Charles, Charles.
我妹妹
My sister...
死于一场车祸
got herself killed in a car crash.
玛西，别跑得太远!
Not too far now, Marcee!
她那个鲁莽的丈夫醉过了头
Her cowboy husband was too drunk
都没法意识到他醉过了头没法开车
to know that he was too drunk to drive.
所以，我收养了她
So, I took her in.
她怎么个子这么小
She's so small.
因为她还是个孩子嘛，孩子都这样
She's young, John. That's how they come.
我在哈佛大学...
I'm at Harvard...
主持伟大作家研讨会
doing the great author's workshop.
他娘的D.H.劳伦斯
D.H. Bloody Lawrence.
你实在该去买本新书啦
I really do think you should buy yourself a new book.
唔，我可一直能听到你的消息
Well, I've been reading a lot about you.
近来还好吧，约翰?
How are you, John?
刚开始我的工作很鸡毛蒜皮
At first all my work here was trivial,
但现在有了新的进展，可惜...
but a new assignment came up and...
不能告诉你细节
I can't really tell you any details.
最高机密? 黑袋子? 黑色行动?
Top secret? Black bag? Black ops?
差不多啦
Something like that.
还有...
And, uh...
嗯?
Yes?
呃，我...我遇见了一个女孩
Well, I... I met a girl.
不是吧! 一个人类女孩?
No! A human girl?
-是一个智人  -一个两足动物?
-Homo sapiens.  -A biped?
嗯，而且万万没想到的是
Yup. And contrary to all probabilities,
她居然在一些层面很喜欢我
she finds me attractive on a number of different levels.
真的?
Really?
天，那真是太棒了!
God, that's wonderful!
萝卜白菜各有所爱，是吧?
There's no accounting for taste, is there?
我该向她求婚吗?
Should I marry her?
对，这得考虑
Oh, God. Right.
话说，现在一切都还不错
I mean, everything's going well.
工作稳定，我也存够了钱
The job is fine. I have enough money.
似乎已经万事具备，可是...
It all seems to add up. But...
怎么才能确定呢?
how do you know for sure?
天下没有确定的事，约翰
Nothing's ever for sure, John.
这是我唯一可以确定的
That's the only sure thing I do know.
艾丽西娅，别生气好吗
Alicia, please don't be angry.
我一忙就忘了时间...
I just lost track of time at work...
又犯了
again.
对不起
I'm sorry.
我来不及包装一下
I didn't have time to wrap it.
生日快乐
Happy birthday.
玻璃的折射面，你瞧
The refractive faces of the glass, you see,
它们可以创造全波长的分布
they create a full wavelength dispersal,
所以如果往里面看，你能看到...
so if you look inside it, you can see...
所有可能的颜色
Every possible color.
还记得你说过上帝一定是个画家
Remember you said that time God must be a painter,
才会有这么多种颜色吗? 在州长家...
because of all the colors? At the governor's house...
你说过的
you said that.
我以为你没在听
I didn't think you were listening.
我一直在听
I'm always listening.
它真美
It's beautiful.
艾丽西娅，我们的关系是否能保证长远的承诺呢?
Alicia, does our relationship warrant long-term commitment?
我需要一点证明
Because I need some kind of proof,
一些可验证的，能作为依据的资料
some kind of verifiable, empirical data.
抱歉，给我一点时间...
I'm sorry, just give me a moment...
让我少女心的浪漫观念调整一下
to redefine my girlish notions of romance.
一个证明?  可验证的资料
A proof? Verifiable data.
嗯...好吧
Um... okay.
宇宙有多大?
Well, how big is the universe?
无限大
Infinite.
你怎么知道?
How do you know?
因为所有的资料是这么指示的
I know because all the data indicate it.
-可是它还没被证实对吗?  -没有
-But it hasn't been proven yet?  -No.
-你也没亲眼见过  -没有
-You haven't seen it.  -No.
那你怎能确定呢?
How do you know for sure?
不知道，我只是相信
I don't, I just believe it.
我想，这和爱一样
It's the same with love, I guess.
现在，你所不知道的部份...
Now, the part that you don't know...
是我愿不愿意嫁给你
is if I want to marry you.
对着相机笑一笑!
Smile for the camera!
太棒了! 噢，小甜心
Well done! Oh, sweet pea.
-我爱你  -恭喜你
-I love you.  -Congratulations.
你真美
You look beautiful.
嗨，你好吗?
Hi, how are you?
坎 布 里 奇 ， 麻 省
1 9 5 4 年   1 0 月
美国政府
上车，快
Get In. Hurry.
他们在跟踪我们
They're following us.
谁...谁在跟踪我们?
Who's... Who's following us?
这个投信点已被放弃了
The drop's been compromised.
躺下去!
Get down!
别起来
Stay down.
这个，拿去
Here, take this.
我不会开枪杀人
I ain't shooting anybody.
-快他妈拿上枪!  -不!
-Take the goddamn gun!  -No!
你这个混...
Son of a...
往后靠，别动
You stay back. Don't move.
约翰?
John?
嗨
Hi.
你去哪儿了?
Where were you?
-苏...  -嗯，我跟苏谈过了
-S-Sol...  -Yeah, I talked to Sol.
他说你离开办公室好几个钟头了
He said you left the office hours ago.
怎么不打个电话给我?
Why didn't you call me?
你没事吧?
Are you all right?
宝贝?
Honey?
约翰...拜托，告诉我，告诉我出什么事了
John... Please, talk to me. Tell me what happened.
约翰，开门
John, open the door.
别这样，快开门! 让我进去!
Come on, open the door! Let me in!
你说话呀! 约翰!
Talk to me! John!
开门!
Open the door!
小心车，孩子
Watch for cars, kids.
约翰
John.
威廉，这和我当初参加的本意不符
William. This is not what I signed on for.
每次有车子回火或者有门关上...
Every time a car backfires or a door slams...
我懂...非常明白
I understand... better than you could possibly imagine.
你需要冷静下来，约翰
You need to calm down, John.
听我说，我们就快找到原子弹了
Now listen to me. We're closing in on the bomb,
大部分归功于你的工作
in large part due to your work.
你不觉得你的恐惧只是很微小的代价吗?
Now don't you think your fear is a small price to pay?
威廉，我的情况已经变了
William, my circumstance has changed.
艾丽西娅怀孕了
Alicia's pregnant.
我告诉过你有家室会增加危险性
I told you attachments were dangerous.
你还是选了结婚
You chose to marry the girl.
我并没有阻止
I did nothing to prevent it.
确保大家安全的最好办法
The best way to ensure everybody's safety
就是你继续你的工作
is for you to continue your work.
我会甩手不干的
Well, I'll just quit.
你不会的
You won't.
凭什么?
Why would I not?
因为你在替我工作的事儿是我瞒住了俄国人
Because I keep the Russians from knowing you work for us.
你要是不帮我了
You quit working for me,
那我也不帮你了
I quit working for you.
帕彻! 帕彻!
Parcher! Parcher!
约翰，你没事吧
John, you all right?
约翰?
John?
把它关了! 把灯关了!
Turn it off! Turn off the light!
你干嘛那么做?
Why would you do that?
你干嘛要把灯打开?
Why would you turn the light on?
你是怎么了?
What is wrong with you?
你得去你姐姐家
You have to go to your sister's.
我把车停在后面了，你走康门威尔茨路
I left the car out the back, and you take Commonwealth.
别开小路，挑人多的地方走
No side streets, you stay where it's crowded.
约翰，我哪儿也不去!
John, I'm not going anywhere!
到你姐姐家以后，你就等我电话
When you get to your sister's, you wait for me to call you.
不，我不去
No, I'm not going.
快把你东西收拾好
Just get your things.
-我不走...  -别吵! 别吵了!
-I'm not leaving...  -Stop! Stop it!
艾丽西娅，求求你
Please, Alicia.
方便的时候我会解释的
I'll explain when I can.
哈     佛     大     学
全    国    数    学    研    讨    会
约翰叔叔!
Uncle John!
嘿，小宝贝!
Hey, baby girl!
哇，有人需要抱一个
Wow, someone needed a hug.
我看到你在演讲名单上，就想...
I saw you on the slate and I thought to myself,
"我怎么能错过高不可攀的
"How can I miss seeing a guest lecture
约翰・纳什的客座演讲?"
by the inimitable John Nash"?
哪里不对了?
What's wrong?
我淌进了一股混水，可能需要你帮忙
I got myself into something. I think I might need some help.
唔，那你告诉我，怎么回事?
Well, now you tell me, what is it?
纳什教授!
Professor Nash!
欢迎!
Welcome!
再说吧?
After?
所以我们能发现...
So, we see that the... the zeroes,
黎曼复变函数中的零
of the Riemann zeta function,
对应着时空中的
correspond to singularities
奇异点
in space-time,
时空中的奇异点，然后...
singularities in space-time. Then...
还有传统的数论...
And conventional number theory...
它在相对论的探索中会失效
it breaks down in the face of relativistic exploration.
有时数字会背叛我们的预期
Sometimes our expectations are betrayed by the numbers.
变量不可能被赋以任何
Variables are impossible to assign any...
有理数值
rational value.
纳什教授!
Professor Nash!
-等等!  -纳什教授?
-Hold it!  -Professor Nash?
纳什教授
Professor Nash,
请别把事情闹大，好吗?
let's avoid a scene, shall we?
你想干什么?
What do you want?
我叫罗森
My name is Rosen,
罗森医生，我是一名精神病专家
Dr. Rosen. I'm a psychiatrist.
不好意思我可不信
Forgive me if I don't seem persuaded.
希望你能和我一起走，约翰
I'd like you to come with me, John.
只是谈谈而已
Just for a chat.
看来我没有选择的余地
It appears I have no choice.
救命! 来人啊!
Help me! Somebody!
来人啊! 救命!
Somebody! Help me!
别碰我!
Get off me!
我知道你是谁! 我知道你是谁!
I know who you are! I know who you are!
不不不，别
No, no, no, no, don't.
查尔斯，他们是俄国人! 查尔斯，他们是俄国人!
Charles, they're Russians! Charles, they're Russians!
去叫人! 去叫人，查尔斯!
Call somebody! Call somebody, Charles!
-他们是俄国人!  -稳住他的腿
-They're Russians!  -Steady the leg.
离我远点，别过来!
Get away from me. Stay away from me!
你瞧
There, now.
好多了吧
All better.
这里没事了
Everything's all right here.
小心头
Watch your head.
约翰?
John?
你能听到我说话吗?
Can you hear me?
现在放松
Go easy now.
麻醉药效得要一会儿才会消失
Thorazine takes a little while to wear off.
抱歉把你铐起来
Sorry about the restraints.
你的右钩拳可真厉害
You've got one hell of a right hook.
我在哪儿?
Where am I?
麦克阿瑟精神病医院
Macarthur Psychiatric Hospital.
我对此非常怀疑
I find that highly unlikely.
你搞错了
You made a mistake.
我的工作和军事无关
My work is non-military in application.
哪种工作，约翰?
Which work is that, John?
我什么也不知道
I don't know anything.
死守秘密没有好处，你明白吧
There's no good in keeping secrets, you know.
查尔斯?
Charles?
我无意把你牵扯进来
I didn't mean to get you involved in this.
对...对不起
I'm... I'm sorry.
查尔斯?
Charles?
浪子室友原形毕露了
The prodigal roommate revealed.
"看到我的名字在演讲名单上"?
"Saw my name on the lecture slate"?
你这狗日的骗子!
You lying son of a bitch!
你在和谁说话? 告诉我你看到谁了
Who are you talking to? Tell me who you see.
"查尔斯・赫曼" 用俄语怎么说?
How do you say, "Charles Herman" in Russian?
这个用俄语怎么说?
How do you say it in Russian?
那里没人，约翰，那里没人
There's no one there, John. There's no one there.
他就在那儿，他就在那儿
He's right there. He's right there.
住手! 我什么都不知道!
Stop! I don't know anything!
住手! 我...我什么都不知道!
Stop! I... I don't know anything!
我叫约翰・纳什
My name is John Nash.
我被强制拘禁了
I'm being held against my will.
谁去联络国防部
Somebody call the Department of Defense.
我叫约翰・纳什
My name is John Nash.
我被强制拘禁了!
I'm being held against my will!
他是怎么了?
What's wrong with him?
约翰得了精神分裂症
John has schizophrenia.
得这种病的人通常都会产生妄想
People with this disorder are often paranoid.
可...可他的工作
But... But his work.
他在处理谋叛方面的事，所以...
He deals with conspiracies, so...
是，是，我知道
Yes, yes, I know.
在约翰的世界里，这种行为是...被接受的
In John's world, these behaviors are... accepted,
被鼓励的
encouraged.
鉴于此，他的病情可能一直未得到处理
As such, his illness may have gone untreated
远比一般情形要久
far longer than is typical.
你想说什么? 有多长?
What do you mean? How long?
可能在研究生院就开始了?
Possibly since graduate school?
至少他的幻觉是从那时开始的
At least that's when his hallucinations seem to have begun.
你在说什么? 什么幻觉?
What are you talking about? What hallucinations?
目前为止，有一个是我已经发现的
One, so far, that I am aware of.
一名叫查尔斯・赫曼的虚构室友
An imaginary roommate named Charles Herman.
查尔斯并不是虚构的
Charles isn't imaginary.
他和约翰自普林斯顿时起就是最好的朋友
He and John have been best friends since Princeton.
你见过查尔斯吗? 他到你们家吃过饭吗?
Have you ever met Charles? Has he ever come to dinner?
每次他来城里都只停留很短时间，忙着演讲
He's always in town for so little time, lecturing.
你的婚礼他在吗?
Was he at your wedding?
他得教书呀
He had to teach.
你看过他哪怕一张照片
Have you ever seen a picture of him,
-和他在电话上聊过吗?  -这太荒谬了
-talked to him on the telephone?  -This is ridiculous.
我致电普林斯顿了
I phoned Princeton.
根据他们的宿舍记录
According to their housing records,
约翰是一个人住
John lived alone.
想想看，哪个更有可能...是你先生
Now, which is more likely... that your husband,
一名未受过军事训练的数学家
a mathematician with no military training,
成为逃避俄国人追杀的政府间谍
is a government spy fleeing the Russians...
你说得他好像疯了一样
You're making him sound crazy.
还是，他失去了对现实的掌控?
Or, that he has lost his grip on reality?
现在我能帮他的唯一方法
Now the only way I can help him
是告诉他真实存在的
is to show him the difference
和仅存在于他
between what's real
头脑中的事物的差别
and what is in his mind.
来吧
Come on.
他都在做些什么?
What's he been working on?
他的工作是机密
His work is classified.
他提到了一名监管者
He mentioned a supervisor
名叫威廉・帕彻
by the name of William Parcher.
也许帕彻先生能让我们搞清状况
Maybe Mr. Parcher can clarify things for us.
但是没有许可我不能找他
But I can't get to him without clearances.
你要我帮你找出
You want me to help you get
我先生工作的细节?
the details of my husband's work?
约翰认为我是苏俄间谍
John thinks I'm a Russian spy.
你也这么觉得?
Is that what you think?
-医生怎么说?  -他病了吗?
-What did the doctor say?  -Is he sick?
不知道
I don't know.
我要看看约翰都在做些什么
I want to see what John's been working on.
你知道你不能进他办公室的
You know you can't go in his office.
那都是机密，艾丽西娅
It's classified, Alicia.
停下
Stop.
我的天
Oh, my God.
你们怎么都不提一句呢?
Why didn't you say something?
艾丽西娅，约翰向来...
Alicia, John's always been...
就有点怪
a little weird.
他说他在做破解密码的工作
He said he was doing code-breaking,
禁止外传的那种
that it was eyes-only.
-最高机密，军事行动的一部分  -是吗?
-Top secret, part of the military effort.  -Was he?
唔，是有可能的，你知道吧?
Well, it was possible, you know?
指令不断地下达
Directives come down all the time
许多东西我们都不清楚
that some of us aren't cleared for.
是有可能的
It was possible.
有可能，但...
Possible, but...
又不像
not likely.
最近他变得很惊慌
Lately, he'd become so much more agitated
然后你打电话来...
and then when you called...
所以说，他每天只做这些吗?
So, is this all he's been doing every day?
剪剪杂志而已?
Cutting out magazines?
呃，不全是
Well, not all.
-对不起!  -没事儿
-I'm so sorry!  -It's okay.
-我想你  -我也想你
-I missed you.  -I missed you.
我得和你谈谈
I have to talk to you.
好
Okay.
艾丽西娅，我一直在反思
Alicia, I've been thinking about it,
我知道我的所做所为
and I do realize that my behavior
以及不能与你讨论这些状况
and my inability to discuss the situation with you
肯定显得很疯狂
must have appeared insane.
我让你别无选择
I left you with no other choice.
这点我非常明白...
I do understand...
我也万分抱歉
and I'm truly sorry.
没关系
That's okay.
一切都会好起来的
Everything's gonna be all right.
我们必须小声说话
We just have to talk quietly.
他们可能在偷听，这里可能有窃听器
They may be listening. There may be microphones.
我现在要告诉你所有事情
I'm gonna tell you everything now.
这会破坏当初的协议
It's breaking with protocol
但你必须得知道
but you need to know,
因为你得帮我逃出这里
because you have to help me get out of here.
我一直在替政府做最高机密的工作
I've been doing top-secret work for the government.
现在存在着一股威胁
There's a threat that exists
它将导致巨大的灾变
of catastrophic proportions.
俄国人大概认为我的目标太大了
I think the Russians feel my profile is too high.
所以他们没有直接做掉我
That's why they simply just don't do away with me.
他们把我关在这里好让我没法继续工作
They're keeping me here to try to stop me from doing my work.
你要到惠勒研究室去
You have to get to Wheeler.
你要找到威廉・帕彻
You have to find William Parcher.
他可以帮我们
He can help us.
别说了!
Stop!
我去过惠勒研究室
I went to Wheeler.
很好，很好
Good, good.
那里没有威廉・帕彻
There is no William Parcher.
绝对有的，我一直在替他工作
Of course there is. I've been working for him.
做什么?
Doing what?
破解密码吗?
Breaking codes?
把包裹投递到秘密投信箱里
Dropping packages in a secret mailbox
让政府去拿吗?
for the government to pick up?
你怎么会知道?
How could you know that?
苏跟踪过你
Sol followed you.
-他觉得没有害处  -苏跟踪过我?
-He thought it was harmless.  -Sol followed me?
它们根本没被拆开过
They've never been opened.
这不是真的
It isn't real.
没有什么谋叛，约翰
There is no conspiracy, John.
没有什么威廉・帕彻
There is no William Parcher.
这是你脑子里的东西
It's in your mind.
你明白了吗，宝贝?
Do you understand, baby?
你病了
You're sick.
你病了，约翰
You're sick, John.
约翰?
John?
约翰!
John!
红色警报，罗森医生，红色警报，请到二号观察室
Code red. Dr. Rosen, code red. Observation room two.
罗森医生，红色警报，请到二号观察室
Dr. Rosen, code red. Observation room two.
约翰?
John?
约翰
植入体不见了
The implant's gone.
我找不到了
I can't find it.
它消失了
It's gone.
知道吗，精神分裂症最大的痛苦
You see, the nightmare of schizophrenia
是分不清何为真实
is not knowing what's true.
想想看...
Imagine...
如果你突然发现对你最重要的
if you had suddenly learned that the people and the places
那些人，那些事，那些时刻
and the moments most important to you
不是消失了，不是死去了
were not gone, not dead,
而是更糟糕...
but worse...
从未存在过
Had never been.
那该是怎样的煎熬苦难啊?
What kind of hell would that be?
注射胰岛素
Administering insulin.
上午 8:42
8:42 am.
多久一次?
How often?
一周五次，一共十周
Five times a week for 10 weeks.
普    林    斯    顿    大    学
一      年      后
约翰对在普林斯顿的日子总是津津乐道
John always spoke so fondly of being here at Princeton.
而且汉森现在负责掌管整个系了
And Hansen is running the department now.
他还老是跟我们提，跟我们提
So he keeps reminding us, and reminding us.
可惜约翰不肯走近校园一步
John won't come near the campus, though.
我想他是觉得难为情
I think he's ashamed.
呀，呀
Hey. Hey.
要这个吗?
Want this?
所以，艾丽西娅，你...你是怎么撑下来的?
So, Alicia, how... how are you holding up?
嗯，他的幻觉已经消失了
Well, the delusions have passed.
他们说药物和没有压力的环境...
They're saying with the medication and low stress environment...
不，我...我问的是你
No, I... I mean, how are you?
我常在想我感觉到的...
I think often what I feel...
是一种义务
is obligation.
或是对想过离开他的内疚
Or guilt over wanting to leave.
一股愤怒，对约翰、上帝和...
Rage against John, against God and...
可是...
But...
随后我注视着他
then I look at him
逼自己把他视为我的那个白马王子
and I force myself to see the man that I married.
然后他就是了
And he becomes that man.
他变成了我深爱的人
He's transformed into someone that I love.
而我也变成了深爱他的人
And I'm transformed into someone who loves him.
虽然不是每次都可以，但...
It's not all the time, but...
也足够了
it's enough.
约翰真是个幸运的男人，艾丽西娅
I think John is a very lucky man, Alicia.
又是多么不幸呐
So unlucky.
-这就是我们家  -这就是了?
-This is us.  -This is it?
-很不错  -离我上班的地方近
-It's nice.  -It's near where I work.
约翰? 有人来看你啦
John? You've a visitor.
嗨
Hi.
希望你不介意
I hope it's okay.
你好啊，老板
Hey ya, chief.
-抽烟吗?  -啊，不抽，谢了
-Cigarette?  -Ah, no, thanks.
我戒了
I quit, actually.
-哈  -嘿，约翰
-Hello.  -Hey, John.
-来认识一下哈维吧?  -哈维?
-Have you met Harvey?  -Harvey?
-我...约翰，这里没有...  -别紧张，没事儿
-I... John, there's no...  -Relax, it's okay.
变成疯子也让我找到一点儿乐子
There's no point in being nuts if you can't have a little fun.
天啊，约翰
Jesus Christ, John.
真被你唬到了
You know, I should have known.
药在这里
Here you go.
我想等下再吃
I can take those later.
你现在就该吃了
You're supposed to take them now.
我给你拿点什么喝?
Can I bring you something?
不用麻烦了
I'm okay.
好
Okay.
唔，我...我是来这里
So, yeah. I... I was in town
主持一个研讨会
giving a workshop.
今晚就得回去
I go back tonight.
你知道的，本德尔，他很想来
You know, Bender, he really wanted
拜访一下，看看你，打个照面
to stop by and you know, see you. You know, say hi.
但他害怕?
Squeamish?
是的
Yeah.
估计换作是我也一样
I suppose I would be, too.
可是哎呀，我却被自己缠上了
But alas, I'm stuck with me.
我正试着解决黎曼假设
I'm trying to solve the Riemann Hypothesis.
喔，是吗?
Oh, yeah?
我觉得要是...要是我能让他们刮目相看
I figured if... if I dazzle them,
他们就该让我复职了
they will have to reinstate me.
但因为药物的影响就很困难
But it's difficult with the medication,
很难看出...
because it's hard to...
它的解
see the solution.
知道吗，约翰，你应该放松的
You know, John, you should go easy.
还有许多别的事可做...
There are other things besides...
除了工作
Besides work.
都有什么呢?
What are they?
你在想什么呢?
What are you thinking about?
人们都做些什么?
What do people do?
都在生活，约翰
It's life, John.
做可以做的事情
Activities available,
增添一点儿意义
just add meaning.
你可以试着走出家门
You could try leaving the house.
或许可以...
You know, maybe...
和邻居们闲聊
talk to people.
你可以试着把垃圾拿出去
You could try taking out the garbage.
那儿还有一些...还有一些在...
And there's some more... there's some more in...
你...你在跟谁讲话?
Who... Who were you talking to?
收垃圾的人
Garbage man.
收垃圾的人晚上不来的
Garbage men don't come at night.
也许这一块儿的回来
I guess around here they do.
对不起
Sorry.
是因为吃药的关系吗?
Is it the medication?
我不知道该怎么办
I don't know what to do.
今晚上我妈带孩子会带久一点
My mother's going to keep the baby a little longer tonight.
这样我就能再加三小时的班
I can get three hours of overtime.
我去睡了
I'm going to bed.
-晚安  -晚安
-Good night.  -Good night.
很高兴见到你，约翰
It's good to see you, John.
好久不见了
It's been a while.
帕彻?
Parcher?
是的，长官
Yes, sir.
你不是真的!
You're not real!
我当然是，别说胡话了
Of course I am. Don't be ridiculous.
我觉得我是不会走那边的，约翰
I don't think that I would go that way, John.
是时候让你回来工作了
It's time for you to get back to work.
原子弹已经抵达最终位置了
The bomb is in its final position
就在美国境内
here in the U.S.
我们知道你的状况
Knowing your situation
你不得不保持低调，先知
requires you keep a low profile, "Mohammed",
所以我们为了你搬过来了
we've brought the mountain to you.
我们把原子弹的位置范围
We've narrowed the bomb's location
缩小到东部沿海某地了
to somewhere on the eastern seaboard.
可是一直没法找出确定的地点
But we haven't been able to pinpoint its exact position.
他们的密码越来越复杂了
Their codes have grown increasingly complex.
来，看看这个，约翰
Here, look at this, John.
怎么?
What?
罗森医生说...
Dr. Rosen said...
罗森! 那个江湖郎中!
Rosen! That quack!
"精神分裂症导致虚构现实"，对不对?
"Schizophrenic break from reality," right?
心理医生的屁话! 看着我，约翰
Psychological bullshit! Look at me, John.
约翰，看着我
John, look at me.
我看着像幻觉吗?
Do I look like I'm imagined?
惠勒研究室没有你的资料
Wheeler has no record of you.
你觉得我们会留人事资料?
Do you think we list our personnel?
约翰，对不起让你经历这一切
John, I'm sorry you had to go through all this.
我花了很大一番功夫才把你弄回来
I've gone to a great deal of trouble to get you back.
我可以恢复你在惠勒研究室的身份
I can restore your status at Wheeler.
我可以让世界知道你的贡献
I can let the world know what you did.
但我现在需要你，士兵
But I need you now, soldier.
当时以为你不是真的可把我吓坏了
I was so scared you weren't real.
普  林  斯  顿  ，  新  泽  西  州
1 9 5 6 年  4 月
暴风雨要来了
There's a storm coming.
我去把衣服收进来，好吗?
I'm just going to grab the laundry, okay?
我去给他洗澡
I'll draw his bath.
你放心
It's okay.
好
Okay.
约翰!
John!
我就快弄完了! 查尔斯，你看好孩子啊
I've almost got it! Charles, you just watch the baby.
-还要关最后一扇!  -不!
-I've got one more to close!  -No!
我马上过去
I'll be right there.
噢，天啊
Oh, God.
我需要条毛巾
I need a towel.
查尔斯在照看他，没事的
Charles was watching him. He was okay.
这里根本没有人
There is no one here.
-查尔斯在照看他  -这里根本没有人!
-Charles was watching him.  -There is no one here!
他被注射了隐形血清
He's been injected with a cloaking serum.
我之所以能看到他是因为
I can see him because of a chemical
以前的植入物溶解后在我血液里
that was released into my bloodstream
释放了一种化学物质
when my implant dissolved.
我没法告诉你，是为了你自己的安全!
I couldn't tell you, it was for your own protection!
艾丽西娅!
Alicia!
-不要!  -喂，请替我接罗森医生办公室
-No!  -Hello, I need Dr. Rosen's office, please.
你得阻止她，约翰
You've got to stop her, John.
你别把她牵扯进来
You leave her out of this.
你在跟谁说话?
Who are you talking to?
这不是她的错
It's not her fault.
约翰
John.
她会又坑我们一次的
She'll compromise us again.
不，她不会的
No, she won't.
你会又回医院里去的
You'll go back to the hospital.
约翰，回答我!
John, answer me!
无数的人将会死亡
Countless people will die.
艾丽西娅，求你，把电话放下
Alicia, please, put the phone down.
-我不能允许它发生  -你好?
-I can't let that happen.  -Yes, hello?
我找罗森医生，他在吗?
Hi, I need Dr. Rosen. Is he in?
抱歉了，约翰
I'm sorry, John.
不――!
No-oo!
艾丽西娅?
Alicia?
-你知道你该怎么做，纳什  -离我远点
-You know what you have to do, Nash.  -Get away from me.
她太危险了
She's too great a risk.
走开!
Get away!
我不是故意伤害你的!
I didn't mean to hurt you!
干掉她，她知道的太多了
Finish her. She knows too much now.
约翰叔叔?
Uncle John?
你去处理掉她，你这下贱的狗屎
You take care of her, you pathetic piece of shit,
否则我就处理掉你
or I'll take care of you.
约翰
John,
噢天啊，约翰，拜托快按他说的去做
Oh Christ, John, please do what he says.
行动，士兵
Move, soldier.
马上
Now.
约翰叔叔?
Uncle John?
约翰，拜托!
John, please!
马上!
Now!
我明白了
I understand.
她一直没有长大
She never gets old.
玛西不可能是真的，她一直没有长大
Marcee can't be real. She never gets old.
你现在看得到他们吗?
You see them now?
是的
Yes.
为什么停止服药?
Why did you stop your meds?
因为我没法工作
Because I couldn't do my work.
我没法帮忙照顾孩子
I couldn't help with the baby.
我没法...
I couldn't...
我没法回应我妻子的需要
I couldn't respond to my wife.
你觉得那比做疯子要强吗?
You think that's better than being crazy?
我们得让你接受更高强度的
We'll need to start you on a higher run
胰岛素震疗和新型药物
of insulin shocks and a new medication.
不
No.
一定还有别的办法
There has to be another way.
精神分裂症非常不稳定
Schizophrenia is degenerative.
有些时候不会发病
Some days may be symptom-free,
但拖得越久，情况会越糟糕
but over time, you are getting worse.
它就是一个问题，仅此而已
It's a problem. That's all it is.
它就是一个还没有解的问题
It's a problem with no solution.
而那正是我的专长，我总能解出问题
And that's what I do, I solve problems.
-这是我最擅长的  -这不是数学
-That's what I do best.  -This isn't math.
你没法写出一行公式
You can't come up with a formula
来改变你对世界的认知
to change the way you experience the world.
我只需要运用我的脑子就行
All I have to do is apply my mind.
没有什么定理，没有什么证明
There's no theorem, no proof.
你没法用理性思维去解决
You can't reason your way out of this.
凭什么? 我凭什么不行?
Why not? Why can't I?
因为你的脑子正是问题的发源地
Because your mind is where the problem is in the first place.
我做得到
I can do this.
我能想出办法，只要给我时间
I can work it out. All I need is time.
是孩子在叫吗?
Is that the baby?
孩子在我妈那儿，约翰
The baby's at my mother's, John.
如果不去治疗，约翰
Without treatment, John,
你可能会被你的幻想...
the fantasies may take over...
完全控制
entirely.
你快整理好了吗?
You almost ready?
罗森在外面等你
Rosen's waiting outside.
我不能再回到医院去
I can't go back to that hospital.
去了就回不来了
I won't come home.
他说如果你这么说的话
He said that if you said that,
他为我准备了强制委托书
he has commitment papers for me to sign.
唔，也许你不会签的
Well, maybe you won't sign them.
也许你会多给我点时间
Maybe you'll just give me some time.
我会找出解决的方法
I will try to figure this out.
不管你怎么定
Whatever you do,
罗森有一点说对了
Rosen is right about one thing.
你不该留在这儿
You shouldn't be here.
我可能会伤害到你
I'm not safe anymore.
你真会伤害我吗，约翰?
Would you have hurt me, John?
我不知道
I don't know.
也许你应该让罗森医生把你送去你妈那儿
Maybe you should let Dr. Rosen drive you to your mother's.
罗森说如果你想杀我什么的就马上打电话给他
Rosen said to call if you try and kill me or anything.
你想知道什么是真的吗?
You want to know what's real?
这个
This.
这是真的
This is real.
或许让你...
Maybe the part...
能够从梦里醒过来的东西
that knows the waking from the dream,
或许它不在这儿
maybe it isn't here.
或许它在这儿
Maybe it's here.
我需要去相信
I need to believe
某些非凡的事情是有可能发生的
that something extraordinary is possible.
普    林    斯    顿    大    学
两       个       月       后
进来
Come.
哈，马丁
Hello, Martin.
我的老天爷
Jesus Christ.
不，我...
No. I...
我可不信老天爷，我的救世主情结
I don't have that one. My savior complex
是一种完全不同的形式
takes on a completely different form.
嗯
Yeah.
我都听说了，而且
I heard what happened and well,
我...我想过写信给你，并且寄去了麦克阿瑟医院
I... I wanted to write and I tried you at Macarthur's
但你已经离开了，所以我...
but you'd left, and I just...
这是海林杰的旧办公室
This is Helinger's old office.
对
Yeah.
对，我从他那偷来的
Yeah, I stole it from him.
看来最后还是你赢了，马丁
Seems that you won after all, Martin.
他们都错了，约翰，没有人赢
They were wrong, John. No one wins.
请，快请坐
Please, please have a seat.
天呐，能再见到你太好了
God, it's so good to see you.
什么风把你吹回普林斯顿来了?
What brings you back to Princeton?
约翰?
John?
约翰，抱歉，可你一定得告诉他
John, I'm sorry, but you have to tell him.
告诉他你是个天才，你是个天才，约翰!
Tell him you're a genius. You're a genius, John!
告诉他你的工作至关重要
Tell him your work is critical.
约翰，拜托!
John, please!
你能不能把刚才的事当做没发生过?
Is there any chance that you could ignore what I just did?
当然，老朋友还有什么可说的?
Of course, what are old friends for?
我们的关系当真如此吗，马丁? 是朋友?
Is that what we are, Martin? Friends?
当然了，约翰
John, of course.
当然，我们一直都是
Of course. We always have been.
艾丽西娅和我认为...
Alicia and I think that...
去适应生活，去融入一个集体
that fitting in, being part of a community,
可能对我有益
might do me some good.
一定程度的归属感
That a certain level of attachment,
熟悉的地方，熟悉的人
familiar places, familiar people,
也许能帮我...
might help me...
驱散这些...
elbow out these...
这些脑子里的幻觉
these certain delusions that I have.
要求有点过分，但我还是来了
It's a lot to ask, and now that I'm here,
我也很确定你不会答应
I'm quite certain that you will just say no.
但我在想能不能让我在这儿转一转
But I was wondering if I could hang around.
你需要一间办公室吗?
Will you be needing an office?
不
No.
不用，我在图书馆工作就行
No, I could just work out of the library.
呃，这家伙要进图书馆
Well, this guy tries to wander into the library,
可是他没有身份证
but he doesn't have I.D.
你们这些人就不看备忘录的吗?
Why can't people read their memos, huh?
然后他就整个疯了
Then he goes totally nuts.
不是真的! 你不是真的!
Not real! You're not real!
根本没有什么任务
There's no mission.
噢，糟了，糟了
Oh, shit. Shit.
不是真的! 你不是真的!
Not real! You are not real!
你就这点儿出息吗，士兵?
Is this what you are, soldier?
一具没用的行尸走肉?
Some useless ghoul?
闻名乡里的疯子?
The local madman?
我不是士兵
I'm not a soldier.
你的下场会是在监房里!
You're gonna end up in a cell!
老朽，无用，遭人唾弃
Old, worthless, discarded.
根本没有什么任务
There's no mission.
而你在这摇头晃脑流口水的时候
And while you rock and drool,
这世界正要被烧成灰烬!
the world will burn to ashes!
你不是真的! 你不是真的!
You are not real! You are not real!
那你还在跟我说话，士兵
You're still talking to me, soldier.
根本没有什么任务! 我也不是士兵!
There's no mission! I'm not a soldier!
约翰? 约翰?
John? John?
约翰，约翰! 没事儿了
John, John! It's okay.
我刚刚听说出事儿了，对不起，约翰...
I just heard what happened, I'm sorry. John...
我不是士兵
I'm not a soldier.
约翰，喂，纳什
John. Hey, Nash.
喂，你没事儿了
Hey, you're all right.
女士们先生们，这就是伟大的约翰・纳什!
Ladies and gentlemen, the great John Nash!
约翰?
John?
你真该看看他们当时的表情
You should've seen their faces.
大家都盯着我看
Everybody was just staring at me.
约翰...你知道压力会引起幻觉的
John... you know that stress triggers the delusions.
我知道
I know.
可后来，在回家的路上
But then, on the way home,
查尔斯也在
Charles was there.
有时候，我还真想念跟他的闲聊
Sometimes, I really miss talking to him.
或许罗森是对的
Maybe Rosen's right.
或许我应该考虑再回医院里去
Maybe I have to think about going back into the hospital again.
不
No.
把手给我
Come here.
或许应该明天再试试
Maybe try again tomorrow.
约翰，你不能永远忽视我
John, now, you can't ignore me forever.
查尔斯，你一直是我很好的朋友
Charles, you've been a very good friend to me.
最好的
The best.
但我不会再跟你说话了
But I won't talk to you again.
我真的不行
I just can't.
你也一样，小宝贝
Same goes for you, baby girl.
再见
Good-bye.
我在想能不能旁听你的课
I was wondering if I might audit your course.
这是...这是我的荣幸，纳什教授
It's... It's an honor, Professor Nash.
有什么不对吗?
Is something wrong?
这是我第一次上课
This will be my first class.
早上好
Good morning,
饥渴稚嫩的脑袋们
eager young minds.
这样做不会有用的，约翰
It's never gonna work, John.
你只是在自取其辱
You're just humiliating yourself.
真是可怜!
It's pathetic!
你变得越来越可怜了
You are being pathetic.
我都替你难堪
I'm ashamed of you.
噢，笑死我了
Oh, man!
你们来了么? 就要迟到了
Are you coming? You're gonna be late.
-爸爸，你拿了我的书  -什么?
-Dad, you've got my book.  -What?
你拿了我的书
You've got my book.
噢，给你
Oh, right.
谢谢
Thanks.
-拜拜  -拜
-Good-bye.  -Bye.
晚上见
See you tonight.
拜，亲爱的
Bye, honey.
普    林    斯    顿    大    学
1 9 7 8 年    1 0 月
你是不是解出了黎曼假设?
Did you just solve Riemann?
唔，你怎么看?
Well, what do you think?
那是一个弗罗宾尼斯的非对易扩展的模拟
That's an analog to Frobenius for noncommutative extensions.
对，没错
Yes, it is.
可似乎只是偶尔会成功，所以，没解出来
But it only appears to work sporadically, so, no.
不过...
But...
我相信我已经有所进展了
I believe I'm making progress.
你是...
You're...
你是约翰・纳什，对吗?
You're John Nash, right?
-我是托比・凯利  -你好
-Toby Kelly.  -Hello.
我正在研究你的均衡理论
I've been studying your equilibrium.
你在这儿，在普林斯顿发表的那个
The one you wrote here, at Princeton.
居然能想出一个完全原创的理论，真了不起...
To come up with something totally original, the way you did...
那时我还年轻嘛
You know, I was young.
我在构建一套理论
I've been developing a theory.
我相信我能证明
I believe I can prove
伽罗瓦扩张包含了整个空间
that Galois extensions are covering spaces.
世间万物，世间万物都具有关联性
That everything, everything is connected.
都是同一个主体的一部分
That it's all part of the same subject.
-你上次吃东西是什么时候?  -什么?
-When was the last time you ate?  -Excuse me?
就是吃饭
You know, food.
我太太很喜欢蛋黄酱
My wife, she loves mayonnaise.
噢，谢谢你，谢谢你
Oh, thank you. Thank you.
继续说
Go on.
函数是在...两个范畴内
The function... is in the two categories.
艾丽西娅!
Alicia!
...以最高速度相向行驶...
...coming together at maximum speed of...
咱们假设是十英里每小时
let us say 10 miles per hour.
而在B自行车的轮胎上有只苍蝇
So you have a fly on the tire of bicycle B,
这只苍蝇，每小时可以飞二十英里
and the fly, who can travel at 20 miles an hour,
它离开B自行车的轮胎
leaves the tire of bicycle B and it flies to
飞向A自行车的轮胎，然后再飞回去飞回来
the tire of bicycle A and backwards and forwards
飞回去飞回来，直到两辆自行车相撞
and so on and so forth until the two bikes collide
而可怜的苍蝇被压扁为止
and the poor little fly is squashed.
这就是说在你所处的领域当中
This is the important thing about
全神贯注并且对其融会贯通
actually focusing in and comprehending
是至关重要的
the area that you're dealing with.
数学是非常精细的东西，它也是一种艺术形式
Mathematics is very specific, and it is an art form,
不要管这周围的人怎么跟你说
no matter what these people around here will tell you,
尤其是那些学生物的
especially the people from biology.
不要听信他们任何人
Don't listen to any of those people.
让我说回到你们之前做的东西
Let me go back to what you were doing before.
我说不定会把它们偷走，写本书然后出名
I might want to steal this, write a book and get famous.
我在想我或许可以教书
I was thinking that I might teach.
一班五十个学生
A classroom with 50 students
任何人都会望而生畏的
can be daunting for anyone.
约翰，再说了，你也不是个好老师
John, besides, you're a terrible teacher.
路遥知马力，马丁
I'm an acquired taste, Martin.
我希望自己还能做一点点贡献
I was hoping there still might be something I could contribute.
那那些...
What about the...
呃，你知道的
Well, you know.
他们消失了吗?
Are they gone?
不，他们没有消失
No, they're not gone.
还可能永远都不会消失
And maybe they never will be.
但我已经习惯无视他们了
But I've gotten used to ignoring them
我还觉得到头来他们也有点儿想放弃我了
and I think as a result they've kind of given up on me.
你觉不觉得我们的梦想
You think that's what it's like with
和梦魇也正是如此，马丁?
all our dreams and our nightmares, Martin?
你得不停地饲养它们，让它们活着?
You've got to keep feeding them for them to stay alive?
约翰，可是...他们经常困扰你
John, they... haunt you, though.
他们是我的过去，马丁，每个人都会被其过去所困扰
They're my past, Martin. Everybody's haunted by their past.
好吧，再见啦
Well, good-bye.
约翰，我会和系里谈谈的
John, I'll talk to the department.
也许春季就能开始
Maybe in the spring.
喂，纳什?
Hey, Nash?
你...怕了吗?
You... you scared?
吓呆了
Terrified.
惊呆了，窘呆了
Mortified. Petrified.
蠢呆了，被你
Stupefied by you.
你最好打电话给艾丽西娅
Now you ought best ring Alicia,
-否则你会搞得我...  -我会的
-or you're gonna get me...  -I'll ring her.
摊上大麻烦的
in an awful lot of trouble.
-谢谢，教授  -再见
-Thanks, Professor.  -Good-bye.
-祝您今天过得愉快  -再见
-Have a nice day.  -Good-bye.
普    林    斯    顿    大    学
1 9 9 4 年    3 月
功课一定要做，拜尔先生
Papers in hand, Mr. Beyer.
纳什教授?
Professor Nash?
-你看得到他吗?  -嗯
-Can you see him?  -Yeah.
-你确定?  -嗯哼
-You sure?  -Uh-huh.
肯定? 他在你所见到的景象里?
Positive? He's within your vision?
行，那就好
Okay. Good.
请别介意，我对没见过的人都有点戒心
Forgive me, I'm just always suspicious of new people.
-下礼拜见，教授  -下礼拜见
-See you next week, Professor.  -See you next week.
既然现在我知道你是真的了
So now that I know that you're real,
请问你是哪位，找我有何贵干?
who are you, and what can I do for you?
教授，我是托马斯・金...
Professor, my name is Thomas King...
托马斯・金?
Thomas King?
我是来告知您
and I'm here to tell you
您被考虑授予诺贝尔奖了
that you're being considered for the Nobel prize.
请原谅，我只是有点惊呆了
Forgive me, but I'm just a little stunned.
在过去的几年中
Over the past few years
您的均衡理论已成为现代经济学的基石
your equilibrium has become a cornerstone of modern economics.
-突然间每个人都喜欢它了  -是啊
-Suddenly everybody likes that one.  -Yeah.
那我其它几个类似的项目...
What about my work on other some such projects...
"流形嵌入" 呢?
manifold embedding?
您的议价理论已经应用在
The application of your bargaining problem
联邦电信委员会的宽频拍卖以及反托拉斯案件上...
to F.C.C. bandwidth auctions or to antitrust cases...
-反托拉斯案件?  -不错
-Antitrust cases?  -Yes.
这我倒没料到
I never would have considered that.
我是不是刚好跨出了
Have I just reached
愚蠢的边界，踩到了一点儿紧挨着的正直?
some level of honesty that borders on stupidity?
不不，您可没有
No, no, you haven't.
因为我是想不到那些的
Because I wouldn't have thought of that.
咱们进去喝杯茶?
Shall we have tea?
噢，我不进去那，我通常只是...
Oh, I don't go in there. I usually just...
带着我的三明治去图书馆
take my sandwich in the library.
来吧，约翰，咱们喝杯茶去，今天可是大日子
Come on, John. Let's have some tea. It's a big day.
市场上绝大多数的品牌茶
Most commercially available brands of tea
都不合我的口味
are not suitable to my palate.
我不是...
I'm not...
有一种北印度茶足够浓...
There are some northern Indian teas which are dense enough...
我喜欢那种味道...
I enjoy the flavor that they have...
我已经多少年没进来过了
I have not been in this room for some many years.
不知道他们都有些什么茶
I wonder what tea they serve.
噢，谢谢你，姑娘
Well, thank you, young lady.
这里的变化真大
Things have certainly changed around here.
我有个儿子和她差不多大
I have a son that age.
在哈佛
Harvard.
我本以为诺贝尔奖的提名
I would have thought the nominations
是不会事先公开的
for the Nobel prize would have been secret.
只有在宣布的那一刻才知道
I would have thought you'd only find out if you won or lost.
一般来说是这样的，没错
That is generally the case, yes.
但是这次情况特殊
But these are special circumstances.
这个奖分量很重
The awards are substantial.
而且牵涉到私人基金
They require private funding.
因此...
As such,
诺贝尔奖得主的形象...
the image of the Nobel is...
明白了，你是来看我有没有疯对吧?
I see. You came here to find out if I was crazy?
看我会不会
Find out if I would
真的得了奖后把一切都搞砸?
screw everything up if I actually won?
在主席台上跳舞
Dance around the podium,
一丝不挂然后学鸡叫，类似这种?
strip naked and squawk like a chicken, things of this nature?
差不多啦，嗯
Something like that, yes.
我会不会让你下不来台?
Would I embarrass you?
老实说，有可能
Yes, it is possible.
你知道，我...
You see, I...
我是个疯子
I am crazy.
虽然我在服新药
I take the newer medications,
但还是会产生幻觉
but I still see things that are not here.
我只不过是选择去否认他们
I just choose not to acknowledge them.
就像脑子的节食
Like a diet of the mind,
我选择不放纵自己的某些食欲
I choose not to indulge certain appetites.
比如对我症状的食欲
Like my appetite for patterns.
可能还有对想象和梦的食欲
Perhaps my appetite to imagine and to dream.
纳什教授
Professor Nash.
很高兴你能来这，约翰
It's good to have you here, John.
谢谢
Thank you.
这是一份荣幸，先生
It's an honor, sir.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
荣幸之至，教授
A privilege, Professor.
教授
Professor.
干得好，约翰
Nicely done, John.
谢谢，汤姆
Thank you, Tom.
谢谢
Thank you.
谢谢，艾迪
Thank you, Ed.
这真是我最没有料想到的了
That was certainly most unexpected.
诺   贝   尔   奖   颁   奖   典   礼
斯  德  哥  尔  摩  ，  瑞  典
1  9  9  4  年   1  2  月
谢谢大家
Thank you.
我一直相信数字
I've always believed in numbers.
在方程和逻辑学中
In the equations and logics
它都指向一切的缘由
that lead to reason.
但经过终生的求索
But after a lifetime of such pursuits,
我问自己，逻辑到底是什么?
I ask, what truly is logic?
谁决定了缘由?
Who decides reason?
我的追求带着我遍历了实体世界
My quest has taken me through the physical,
形而上学
the metaphysical,
幻觉
the delusional,
又回到原点
and back.
而我有了生涯中最重要的发现
And I have made the most important discovery of my career.
生命中最重要的发现
The most important discovery of my life.
那就是只有在爱的神秘方程中
It is only in the mysterious equations of love
才能找到合乎逻辑的缘由
that any logical reasons can be found.
今晚我能站在这里全是因为你
I'm only here tonight because of you.
你是我在这里的缘由
You are the reason I am.
你是我所有一切的缘由
You are all my reasons.
谢谢你
Thank you.
非常幸会
So nice to have met you.
我去叫车了，老爸
I'll call for the car, Dad.
拜拜
Bye-bye.
-准备好走了吗?  -噢，是，准备好了
-Are you ready to go now?  -Oh, yes, I am.
早就准备好了
Yes, indeed, and yes, please.
真谢谢你
Thank you so much.
谢谢
Thank you.
怎么啦? 有什么不对吗?
What is it? What's wrong?
没有
Nothing.
什么事也没有
Nothing at all.
跟我走吧，姑娘
Come with me, young lady.
我的车停在外面
I have a car outside.
你想让我载你一程吗?
Are you interested in a ride?
纳什的理论影响了全球贸易谈判，
全国劳工关系，甚至使生物进化学有了重大突破
约翰和艾丽西娅定居在新泽西州普林斯顿
约翰在数学系里每天按时上下班
他仍然天天走路到校园里去